import { createContext, useContext, useEffect, useReducer } from "react";

const questions = [
    {
        question: "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
        options: ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
        correctOption: 1,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question: "Which company invented React?",
        options: ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
        correctOption: 3,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question: "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
        options: ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
        correctOption: 0,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question:
            "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
        options: ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
        correctOption: 2,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question: "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
        options: [
            "From parents to children",
            "From children to parents",
            "Both ways",
            "The developers decides",
        ],
        correctOption: 0,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question: "How to pass data into a child component?",
        options: ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
        correctOption: 1,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question: "When to use derived state?",
        options: [
            "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
            "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
            "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
            "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable",
        ],
        correctOption: 3,
        points: 30,
    },
    {
        question: "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
        options: [
            "Running an effect",
            "Passing props",
            "Updating state",
            "Adding event listeners to DOM elements",
        ],
        correctOption: 2,
        points: 20,
    },
    {
        question: 'When do we directly "touch" the DOM in React?',
        options: [
            "When we need to listen to an event",
            "When we need to change the UI",
            "When we need to add styles",
            "Almost never",
        ],
        correctOption: 3,
        points: 20,
    },
    {
        question: "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
        options: [
            "When updating the state will be slow",
            "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
            "When the state update should happen faster",
            "When the new state depends on the previous state",
        ],
        correctOption: 3,
        points: 30,
    },
    {
        question:
            "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
        options: [
            "On each re-render",
            "Each time we update the state",
            "Only on the initial render",
            "The first time we update the state",
        ],
        correctOption: 2,
        points: 30,
    },
    {
        question:
            "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
        options: ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
        correctOption: 1,
        points: 10,
    },
    {
        question:
            "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
        options: [
            "Usually none",
            "All our state variables",
            "All state and props referenced in the effect",
            "All variables needed for clean up",
        ],
        correctOption: 2,
        points: 30,
    },
    {
        question: "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
        options: [
            "True",
            "It depends on the dependency array",
            "False",
            "In depends on the code in the effect",
        ],
        correctOption: 0,
        points: 30,
    },
    {
        question:
            "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
        options: [
            "Only when the component mounts",
            "Only when the component unmounts",
            "The first time the component re-renders",
            "Each time the component is re-rendered",
        ],
        correctOption: 3,
        points: 20,
    },
];

const SECS_PER_QUESTION = 30;

const initialState = {
    // Questions array which comes from FAKE API
    questions: questions,

    // "loading", "error", "ready", "active", "finished"
    status: "ready",

    // To show questions one by one
    index: 0,

    // Answer
    answer: null,

    // Users points
    points: 0,

    // HighScore
    highscore: 0,

    // Timer
    secondsRemaining: null,
};

function reducer(state, action) {
    switch (action.type) {
        // âœ… Data fetched
        case "dataRecieved":
            return { ...state, questions: action.payload, status: "ready" };
        // âŒ Data rejected
        case "dataFailed":
            return { ...state, status: "error" };
        // ðŸ Start Clicked
        case "start":
            return {
                ...state,
                status: "active",
                secondsRemaining: state.questions.length * SECS_PER_QUESTION,
            };
        // â˜ Answer Clicked
        case "newAnswer":
            // For points learn which question is it.
            const question = state.questions.at(state.index);

            return {
                ...state,
                answer: action.payload,
                /**
                 * Firstly learn which question is it ?
                 * Then compare action.payload with question's correctOption
                 * If true state.points + question's own points
                 * If not, leave as it same
                 */
                points:
                    action.payload === question.correctOption
                        ? state.points + question.points
                        : state.points,
            };
        case "nextQuestion":
            return { ...state, index: state.index + 1, answer: null };

        case "finish":
            return {
                ...state,
                status: "finished",
                highscore:
                    state.points > state.highscore
                        ? state.points
                        : state.highscore,
            };

        case "restart":
            return {
                ...state,
                index: 0,
                answer: null,
                points: 0,
                status: "ready",
                secondsRemaining: 10,
                questions: state.questions
                    .slice()
                    .sort((a, b) => Math.random() - 0.5),
            };
        case "tick":
            return {
                ...state,
                secondsRemaining: state.secondsRemaining - 1,
                status:
                    state.secondsRemaining === 0 ? "finished" : state.status,
            };
        default:
            throw new Error("Action is unknown!");
    }
}

const QuizContext = createContext();

function QuizProvider({ children }) {
    const [
        {
            questions,
            status,
            index,
            answer,
            points,
            highscore,
            secondsRemaining,
        },
        dispatch,
    ] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);

    const numQuestions = questions.length;
    const totalPoints = questions.reduce(function (acc, question) {
        return acc + question.points;
    }, 0);

    // useEffect(function () {
    //     fetch(
    //         `https://codingheroes.io/api-react-course-projects/questions.json`
    //     )
    //         .then(res => res.json())
    //         .then(data => dispatch({ type: "dataRecieved", payload: data }))
    //         .catch(err => dispatch({ type: "dataFailed" }));
    // }, []);

    return (
        <QuizContext.Provider
            value={{
                numQuestions,
                questions,
                totalPoints,
                status,
                index,
                answer,
                points,
                highscore,
                secondsRemaining,
                dispatch,
            }}
        >
            {children}
        </QuizContext.Provider>
    );
}

function useQuiz() {
    const context = useContext(QuizContext);
    if (context === undefined)
        throw new Error("QuizContext used outside of the QuizProvider");
    return context;
}

export { useQuiz, QuizProvider };
